I came here when I was six years old, that's almost 90 years ago.
I walked up that road along there with my mother and father.
They were going to the Victoria and Albert and I'm sure it was my father who was wise
and who knew that I would be bored to tears with the art exhibition that they wanted to see.
I said, look, why don't you go over the road there and see those steam engines they've got there.
So Strand School, bad start, but has improved considerably since half term.
I always regarded school as a kind of prison you were sent to for being young.
I always wanted to be a scientist from at least as early as six years old when I first entered this place.
And I soon discovered that you're not allowed into a laboratory until you have that piece of paper saying you've got a degree.
So I thought, well, I'll just have to soldier on and put up with all this awful schooling.
You're best known probably for Gaia theory. How's that changed in your mind over the past decades?
Very little. It stayed the same thing that it was when it came into my mind in the Jet Propulsion Laboratories in NASA.
Only three years after NASA had been founded.
Where do cities come in?
The nearest model to us in the animal world, the nearest model is the ants and termites, little insects like that.
They learned very early on that the most efficient way of living is to live in a city they call a nest,
where there can even be great air conditioning towers.
Instead of talking about saving the planet, air conditioning the planet,
to air condition a city to the temperature you want is quite easy compared with the planet.
Do you think we should give up trying to save the planet then?
Exactly. Oh yes. That was a nice little lady, that one.
In 1964 I decided that I'd spend the rest of my life as an independent scientist and set up my own lab in a cottage in the village.
I knew I'd have to make my own equipment and it better be good equipment that you make and that requires good instruments to build it with.
And as you can see there it is well used.
Which inventions are most dear to you or do you feel were most important in your life?
Almost impossible to say. I wouldn't classify them any more than I classify people according to their value or importance in life.
They represent challenges, excitements, adventures.
This is the electron capture device here, correct?
Yes.
Tell us what you found with this.
Well I found that the CFCs were adding up in the atmosphere of the world without any apparent loss.
And that the amount that was adding up was almost exactly the amount that industry was releasing into the atmosphere.
I had the chance to go on a ship down to Antarctica and that was my main motivation.
I love sea journeys and I thought oh great I can go down and I can measure the CFCs in the atmosphere all the way from Britain all the way to Antarctica.
And that way estimate what the global atmospheric concentration of the gases are.
So I need an apparatus to do it.
And that took me about three evenings in the country doing that.
Are you at the point where you want to give over the inventing and the science to others or are you working on something now?
No, no. My father was inventing when he was two weeks from dying so I only hope to follow his example.